[SPEAKER_00]: So, to continue that sutta we spoke about last time, we've only got to the third perception that needs to be developed.
[SPEAKER_00]: And this is the fourth one.
[SPEAKER_00]: It says, when a bhikkhu becomes accustomed to the perception of non-delight in regard to the whole world, their mind draws back from the various beautiful things in the world, and either equanimity or
[SPEAKER_00]: The other side gets established.
[SPEAKER_01]: Pretty cool.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, we said in the beginning, the first one was the beautiful side of the ugly, the living side of death, and the necessity of food.
[SPEAKER_01]: Right, right, right.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, the fact that food is the necessity.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're subjected to it and dependent on it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: There's no choice about it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, in itself, it's a burden.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, this is saying, the perception of non-delight... Well, it's to uproot the inherent delight, joy, in regard to the world, in regard to the senses, in regard to the sense objects.
[SPEAKER_00]: By developing what?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, by developing the non-delight.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you develop the non-delight by seeing the danger of delight.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, for example, seeing things you delight in, like everybody... and, you know, delight, the translation... the word delight is not... it's not like you're... you're over the moon ecstatic and delighted.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's... it's... it refers to that subtle attitude of acceptance, of looking forward to, on a mental level, towards things that are pleasing and agreeable.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you delight.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're related.
[SPEAKER_01]: On that mental level, there is joy at the prospect of something pleasant.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, things that are pleasant are not problem in themselves, but it's you being unable to not delight in the prospect of pleasure.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's where the problem is.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because delighting in it means not seeing the inherent danger.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you're seeing the inherent danger in things you are delighting towards, you stop delighting.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're not going to blame those things or, like, try to never see anything agreeable or hear anything agreeable ever again.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's just that you will not delight in it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if it's agreeable, it's known as agreeable, but there's no delight.
[SPEAKER_01]: If it's disagreeable, it's known as disagreeable.
[SPEAKER_01]: There is no, like, resistance to it, which is the opposite of that delight.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, non-delight refers to the absence of delight.
[SPEAKER_01]: It doesn't refer to hating that which you delight in.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes, it's no longer attracted to the beautiful things in the world.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, you are not attracted.
[SPEAKER_01]: That doesn't mean the beautiful things in the world cease to exist.
[SPEAKER_01]: It just means you don't delight in it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you can't just fabricate non-delight out of thin air.
[SPEAKER_01]: Okay, now I'll just practice non-delight.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can only practice non-delight by preventing yourself from delighting in it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And the only way you can prevent yourself from delighting in it is by contemplating, maintaining the context of the danger in things that you are delighting in.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you cultivate non-delights then.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you do that long enough, then you don't have to constantly keep reminding yourself of the danger, because the danger is inherent in those things.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why a freedom from those things is possible in the first place.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it's not seeing the danger, you build up the delight, so to speak, in the course of lifetime... well, lifetimes.
[SPEAKER_00]: You get taken by the... like with food, you get taken with the tastes.
[SPEAKER_00]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: The taste is the... yeah, the taste is the measure.
[SPEAKER_01]: The taste is your motive.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's where your motivation is rooted.
[SPEAKER_01]: And yeah, the food is a good example, because here you can... you can abandon things that are non-essential, like agreeable sight, sound, smell, taste, touches, you restrain from, and you can say no to all of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because, you know, delight in them is bad.
[SPEAKER_01]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_01]: But that still doesn't mean
[SPEAKER_01]: You understood the light simply by saying no to these things, because there are certain things you can't say no to, such as eating.
[SPEAKER_01]: And yes, even the Buddha himself tried to starve himself to death, to see if that would be the way out of complete freedom of the mind, and then he saw actually it isn't.
[SPEAKER_00]: It was being done for the wrong reasons.
[SPEAKER_00]: The food was never the problem.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, things that you can't just say no to, such as food, that's where you have to then practice developing of that context of danger in delighting in it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not the food I'm eating is dangerous, but my delight is the danger.
[SPEAKER_01]: My delight is that which keeps me bound to this aimless wanderings of saṃsāra for eons and eons of time.
[SPEAKER_00]: The danger of delight.
[SPEAKER_01]: The danger of delight.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not the danger of food.
[SPEAKER_01]: The danger of delight in food.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, if there is no delight in it, then, yeah, you wouldn't care what you're eating, good or bad.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's what the Buddha said himself.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's what, I think, Madhyamaka, in that manner, praised him.
[SPEAKER_01]: And he said, what do you see worthy in me of praise?
[SPEAKER_01]: On account of what are you praising me, basically?
[SPEAKER_01]: And he said, oh, Master Gautama is one who eats little, praises eating little.
[SPEAKER_01]: And he has disciples that eat little.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, he missed all these ascetic practices.
[SPEAKER_01]: And he said, that's absolutely not true.
[SPEAKER_01]: I have...
[SPEAKER_01]: I have disciples that sometimes don't eat for two or three days, and yet, sometimes, I would eat... kings and queens would serve me, like, the most refined food you can imagine... manage with their own hands, and I would eat a bowl full to the brim, sometimes two bowls full to the brim.
[SPEAKER_01]: If they were to respect me on account of eating little, they wouldn't, because I don't always eat little.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then he debunks every ascetic practice in itself as a word of respect and says, no, why they respect me is because I've shown them the path out of suffering, I've shown them... and then all these ways of practicing the dhamma that they understood for themselves.
[SPEAKER_01]: So they know important is important and non-important is not important.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like blaming the food and so on, it's not important.
[SPEAKER_01]: Your delight is important.
[SPEAKER_01]: You understand the way out of delight?
[SPEAKER_01]: You wouldn't care if the person who taught you the way out of delight is eating six bowls of food, because you understood what he meant.
[SPEAKER_01]: And even if that person say you learned it from somebody... say you learned it from Sotāpanna, the way out of suffering, and you're practicing it, and you see it in them, that they are not necessarily practicing it.
[SPEAKER_01]: They are eating carelessly.
[SPEAKER_01]: Even that, you wouldn't hold against them, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's just, yeah, it's whatever they do, it's on them.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, whatever they do, does not invalidate the truth of the dhamma, the truth of the instruction that that person has understood.
[SPEAKER_01]: Obviously, the Buddha himself did not eat all this food out of carelessness.
[SPEAKER_01]: He ate because it was necessary to eat, because he was hungry.
[SPEAKER_01]: The hunger was determining how much he'll eat.
[SPEAKER_01]: He didn't seek out kings and queens to serve him food and rejecting law or... No.
[SPEAKER_01]: It just happened to be in such environment, such circumstances.
[SPEAKER_01]: But the point is that if you judge a book by its cover, you will put the cover first and the message of the book second.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it should be the other way around.
[SPEAKER_01]: Even if the cover of the book deteriorates and doesn't necessarily uphold the greatest standard of ascetic practice, is the message basically impenetrable to criticism, the message of freedom from suffering?
[SPEAKER_01]: Is the principle behind freedom from suffering
[SPEAKER_01]: Absolutely true universally.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_01]: You understood it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Doesn't matter if the whole book gets destroyed.
[SPEAKER_01]: Doesn't matter what what a person who told you that do or like in later in the life and so on.
[SPEAKER_01]: What matters is that the message you got, that's the truth.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's what matters.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you measure your practice not by how much you can go without food and how harsh you live and so on.
[SPEAKER_01]: You measure it how...
[SPEAKER_01]: How much more you're free from that delight.
[SPEAKER_01]: How clearer you understood the nature of delight and how more apparent perception of danger in that delight is.
[SPEAKER_01]: And when you would explain that to this man, he's like, oh, yeah, yeah, that is what's worthy of respect.
[SPEAKER_01]: Again, you can easily find things to like or dislike on the on the base of a cover.
[SPEAKER_01]: And sometimes, unfortunately, people would dismiss the message of a person, the teaching, because they don't approve of the cover, or it's not the right color, and so on.
[SPEAKER_01]: Obviously, this man wasn't that shallow, but he was still equating practice with certain just, uh, austere kind of protocols.
[SPEAKER_01]: And he says that's why he's a spiritualist.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not at all.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, yeah, and then the other one was like, sometimes he wears silk robes.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, you know, the silk robes made by boiling bugs to death, so they produce the silk.
[SPEAKER_01]: Obviously, the Buddha did not ask for it, but somebody gave him the silk robes and he accepted it.
[SPEAKER_01]: I mean, from the ascetic point of view, that is absolutely outrageous.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not just that he wears these comfortable silk robes, but also silk was made by killing animals.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, and the Buddha did not say it's an offense, you mustn't wear it.
[SPEAKER_01]: He said you mustn't ask for it to be killed, but if somebody does it and give it to you, it's fine.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then he said he has monks that wear, like, absolute, the most roughest, basically barbed wire type of hemp robes.
[SPEAKER_01]: And if that's the level of what should be respected, they will completely not respect it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's basically knowing the hardwood, as the Buddha would say, from the external appearance of the wood, knowing what's the essence.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's the essence.
[SPEAKER_01]: When it comes to any sensual restraint, you do it first, of course, out of faith, and out of that, kind of creating a buffer zone.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, in itself, things you're restraining against were never the problem.
[SPEAKER_01]: They're a secondary problem.
[SPEAKER_01]: They're a symptom of your problem.
[SPEAKER_01]: Symptom of your delight.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because that's the thing you are directly responsible for.
[SPEAKER_01]: Even when you have a sensual thought appearing in your mind, you did not create it in itself.
[SPEAKER_01]: Now you can choose to entertain it and prolong it and revolve around it.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's a new... and all that comes out of delight.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's what the Buddha would say among dedicated to mindfulness and practice.
[SPEAKER_01]: When a sensual thought arises, he doesn't delight in it.
[SPEAKER_01]: He doesn't welcome it.
[SPEAKER_01]: He doesn't entertain it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And it's the same way we talked about before.
[SPEAKER_01]: If somebody comes at your door,
[SPEAKER_01]: And once you get in, obviously, and now you feel pressured and you open the door, you either go and chase them or let them in and so on.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, the point is to recognize, no, they can't get in unless I let them in.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if I go out, well, that's another way of engaging with it, so they win.
[SPEAKER_01]: If I let them in, that's another way of engaging, so they win again.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, can I endure the pressure at the doorstep without letting it in, without basically losing my control and going out and shouting at them or something?
[SPEAKER_01]: So that's how... and that's how they will leave.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's how you get rid of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: You don't get rid of it by feeding it, by engaging with it, by acknowledging it.
[SPEAKER_01]: You get rid of it by not acting out of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you will not act out of it if you don't delight in it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So delight is a necessary basis for acting towards sensuality.
[SPEAKER_01]: You cannot possibly act towards sensuality unless you're delighting in it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you cannot possibly delight in it, unless you lost or never had the sight of danger in that what you're delighting in.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, cultivate non-delight.
[SPEAKER_01]: You will literally experience dispassion towards the entire world.
[SPEAKER_01]: It doesn't matter.
[SPEAKER_01]: Up, down, left, right, past, future, beautiful, ugly, godly, humanly, whatever.
[SPEAKER_01]: There is no delight in anything that appears for you.
[SPEAKER_00]: And thus you have peaceful, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Absolute.
[SPEAKER_01]: Absolute peace.
[SPEAKER_00]: And perception number five.
[SPEAKER_00]: It says, when a bhikkhu becomes accustomed to the perception of anicca, their mind draws back from acquisitions, honors and fame.
[SPEAKER_00]: And either equanimity gets established, or the other side gets established.
[SPEAKER_01]: So... Yeah, the other side, the counterpart of acquisition, ownership, faith, is a true understanding of that non-ownership, impossibility to own, as we often say when it comes to anicca.
[SPEAKER_01]: See, if things are... Anicca...
[SPEAKER_01]: I've said it before, I won't get into it again, but just to kind of mention again.
[SPEAKER_01]: Anicca is not the impermanence that you can observe.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, look, I destroy this, thus it's impermanent.
[SPEAKER_01]: The destruction of a thing is another thing that has arisen for you.
[SPEAKER_01]: So it's only a relative destruction.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're not destroying your experience as a whole.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're experiencing this is present and now it's all chopped up.
[SPEAKER_01]: That doesn't mean that this is impermanent.
[SPEAKER_01]: It just means it has changed.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you say, ah, so, change.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, anicca is change.
[SPEAKER_01]: But saying everything is changing, it's not personal enough.
[SPEAKER_01]: You want to see that, yeah, everything is changing.
[SPEAKER_01]: But also, me, I am, my experience, the whole, my ownership, my body, my senses, my feelings, my life.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that is also subject to change.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's what I'm saying.
[SPEAKER_01]: Anicca is not about seeing the impermanence, because you can't see the impermanence of your life unless you're dead.
[SPEAKER_01]: But then, you can't see it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if you wait for death to show you that your life is subject to change, well, it's too late.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's the whole point.
[SPEAKER_01]: Saying that something is subject to change, means the possibility of change is inherent in it, without that thing changing.
[SPEAKER_01]: So understanding that things are subject to change, subject to suffering, means understanding that before change, change will have to be inevitable.
[SPEAKER_01]: So you don't wait for it to change.
[SPEAKER_01]: You want to understand that while it's not changing, while your life is there, you want to understand that it's overall, fundamentally, going to change.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, the nature of change is that nature of non-mastery, non-ownership, impossibility to control.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, like, you can control things within their arising, while they're present.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you have a say in your life now.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, fundamentally, you will not have a say when that life decides to change, as in you die.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's like seeing the fundamental basis of your life.
[SPEAKER_01]: Ownership.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Your life.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, whatever you're building up, yeah?
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Honours escalates into fame, escalates into that whole kind of... Extension of yourself.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: Extension of yourself.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's where the Buddha, when he was talking about those different layers of conceit that a monk who practices would remove.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, first, it would be the coarse sensuality and anger and...
[SPEAKER_01]: But then, later on in the practice, he would be removing the thoughts of basically his nationality.
[SPEAKER_01]: As in, on that general level of what you are, where you were, of a greater scale, more subtler.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, of his clan, of his family, of his country, or whatever.
[SPEAKER_01]: Even if you were not necessarily the great national patriot, or something, in your patriginal life, or whatever, you nevertheless, you still identified with the culture, the environment you lived through.
[SPEAKER_01]: And those are subtler acquisitions.
[SPEAKER_01]: But yes, acquisitions, honors, and fame.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, fame is inherently accepted and liked by people.
[SPEAKER_01]: Lack of fame is inherently feared by people.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why people irrationally feel fear of blame.
[SPEAKER_01]: Even if there is no rational basis for a criticism, just the fact that this criticism met you, you're already defending against it and don't want it.
[SPEAKER_01]: It takes a developed mind to not do that, to see through it, though the world warily wins.
[SPEAKER_01]: And all of that comes from simple appropriation of the very things that are in front of you.
[SPEAKER_01]: Your very experience, your very five aggregates, the feelings, the intentions, you already acquire them as yours.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if you contemplate that not this is impermanent, that's impermanent.
[SPEAKER_01]: My experience as a whole, in the utmost sort of general background of I am sitting here talking to you, while the dog is messing around, we are recording, all of that fundamentally is because my body with the senses is here operating and I cannot do anything about that.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that subject to change.
[SPEAKER_01]: As we said in other talks, if your heart would just stop,
[SPEAKER_01]: None of this, my control within it, would be also taken.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, I can control, I can move, I can say yes, I can say no, I can look this way, but all of that is within the non-control.
[SPEAKER_01]: All of that is within the basis that I have no access to.
[SPEAKER_01]: I am not privy to the basis of my aggregates.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, when they change, my entire domain, my entire world, life of control, will be swept away with it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you can recognize that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Through, like, your experience right now, that is in your control, you can recognize that, fundamentally, this is all subjected to change.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's it.
[SPEAKER_01]: You don't have to wait for it to change.
[SPEAKER_01]: You don't need to make it change to prove yourself it's subject to change.
[SPEAKER_01]: You just need to stop acting out of it unwholesomely and discern that, whether you want it or not, the subject of change is implicit.
[SPEAKER_01]: It defines the thing, pretty much.
[SPEAKER_01]: Hence the understanding of anicca.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then there is... then, even if, oh, this is mine, emotionally, there is no acquiring of that, because emotionally, you're already approved... well, you approved your emotions by seeing that they're subject to change.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, how can you then possibly be emotional on account of something secondary to it?
[SPEAKER_00]: You can't take things personally anymore.
[SPEAKER_00]: Impossible.
[SPEAKER_00]: But because you have, you won't go further.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: That perception of Nietzsche won't take you further into taking things personally.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: And it will start undoing.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you cultivate that perception for Nietzsche, sustain it, maintain it in its being, bhavana, literally,
[SPEAKER_01]: It would result in completely fading away of all the acquisitions, which would result in fading away of all the, like, honours, depending on honours, notions of conceit, the greatness, the clan, the belonging, the sense of self in the greatest sense.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you will be completely free of the slightest traces of conceit.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like you're saying the other day, and that's, I think, that's what going forth is.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's the going forth.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's the actually establishing of anicca.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's the real... Well, it's like basically establishing of that my life is subject to anicca in a more kind of acute manner.
[SPEAKER_01]: See, when you live in your home, with your family, with your routine, with your village, with your province, in your country, all of these are like layers and layers and layers of acquisition.
[SPEAKER_00]: Familiarity.
[SPEAKER_01]: Familiarity, exactly, exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: And why is familiarity...
[SPEAKER_01]: Value.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because it doesn't change.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not as often, at least.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, my family, his traditions...
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly, exactly, exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, why do you then... Oh, my family changed.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, but at least we are still the clan.
[SPEAKER_01]: We still have the family name.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, but at least we're this way.
[SPEAKER_01]: At least we're in this country and so on.
[SPEAKER_01]: We, like...
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you have this greater and greater identity.
[SPEAKER_01]: Why?
[SPEAKER_01]: Because it doesn't change as much as the other one.
[SPEAKER_01]: And why do you don't like change?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, because it reminds you of the very, in the very core of your being, you are not your own.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's something that people throughout their entire existence tries to outrun.
[SPEAKER_01]: Try to cover up and keep the lid on.
[SPEAKER_00]: So that's the norm.
[SPEAKER_00]: But then, if someone wants to go forth...
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: You have to remove these false safety zones that you created.
[SPEAKER_01]: You will not understand it immediately.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, some did.
[SPEAKER_01]: As soon as they went forth, they became arahants.
[SPEAKER_00]: But that's the meaning of going forth.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, in a way...
[SPEAKER_01]: Meaning is to start emulating what you need to abandon before it's too late.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's what I mean.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, today, often, you have people just go into their... into the monastery, but it's not really that they left the home.
[SPEAKER_01]: They just replaced one more, like a...
[SPEAKER_01]: A smaller setup of a family and familiarity, with a bigger setup of a bigger family and familiarity, i.e.
[SPEAKER_01]: tradition.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, this is the way, and this is the way, and everybody must... And there's no thinking for oneself, because if you start thinking for yourself, you realize, oh well, all of this is secondary.
[SPEAKER_01]: Tradition, family name, I'm such-and-such monk, this is such-and-such my upajaya, this is what... All of that is secondary.
[SPEAKER_01]: What is first is that you choose to be there for the reasons of safety,
[SPEAKER_01]: But, like, why do I need safety?
[SPEAKER_01]: What are you protecting?
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, you're protecting sense of ownership, you're protecting yourself from anxiety, you're protecting your feelings, you're protecting from uncertainty, because you might overwhelm your mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you realize that today you can have somebody gone forth for decades and still basically a layman, mentally.
[SPEAKER_01]: You just kind of
[SPEAKER_01]: Extended the setup of a home into a bigger area.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, yes, it's not as... it's not as... as... narrowed, as like a little familiarity of my little nook in my house.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you do kind of expand a little bit, but overall, you haven't really... you haven't really abandoned everything.
[SPEAKER_01]: All of these buffer zones that your own conceit needs to protect its own ownership and sense of self.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's... if you're... you're born into the Buddhist tradition.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, yeah, yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: I'm talking...
[SPEAKER_01]: I'm not even talking about that.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, no, that's even more... that's more like... well, that's just... you become part of... You never leave the society by being a priest.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because you're just part of the the social structure, what priests do, for whom... That's your career.
[SPEAKER_00]: You've never left home, still.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_01]: I'm not talking about that.
[SPEAKER_01]: I'm talking for people who do want to practice and kind of go forth, but then you realize...
[SPEAKER_01]: But now you just replaced one familiarity with another familiarity.
[SPEAKER_01]: And now you're afraid to leave this second familiarity.
[SPEAKER_01]: Even to the point of... You remember that... You've seen it many times.
[SPEAKER_01]: People are afraid to change the monastery.
[SPEAKER_01]: Just for a period of time.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or even... Or let alone change the monastery that's in a different tradition.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's just like, whoa, whoa, whoa.
[SPEAKER_01]: But wait, you are homeless.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, why would this be such a big deal?
[SPEAKER_01]: Or like certain places, well, I can't go there because, you know, the routine is too different there.
[SPEAKER_01]: There is no routine.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's the worst fear people would have.
[SPEAKER_01]: When they come, what's your... there is no routine.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're on your own.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, nobody... there's no structure, no traditional authority demanding from you what to do throughout the day.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that is the most frightening thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: If
[SPEAKER_01]: You're basically not honest with yourself fundamentally and realize that that's where the practice is.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, that's where the going forth is.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's where the going forth... literally, there is... and that's what they said.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's... once you do it rightly in the suttas, nothing can match that level of freedom, like a... like a mountain deer.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, anything lower than that would be feeling like a trap in prison.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, dusty.
[SPEAKER_00]: The home life is dusty.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, the home life is crowded and dusty.
[SPEAKER_01]: Many people frequent it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Constant hustle and bustle.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, now, even the monastic life is crowded and dusty.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes, it can be, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: You just go from one... And it happened even in the suttas, when the Buddha reprimanded Ananda, when they were... And they weren't even, like, you know, they were all probably
[SPEAKER_01]: Āryas, at least, or maybe even some of them were arahants.
[SPEAKER_01]: It doesn't matter.
[SPEAKER_01]: When the Buddha came, he was like, what's this noise and racket here?
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, oh, we're sewing robes and organizing cloth, all for a very good purpose.
[SPEAKER_01]: And he told them off for being in a crowd of monks, not like outside the lay people or something.
[SPEAKER_01]: So you could say like, okay, so if that's not acceptable,
[SPEAKER_01]: How much more that's true for, like, just, you know, being fully engaged physically in the crowd, in society, in people, and so on.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, you need to do something, give some teaching one way or the other, but to what extent that compromises the lifestyle of solitude.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you're a monk that's gone from home, from family life,
[SPEAKER_00]: To another temple.
[SPEAKER_00]: Temple life.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, that's even more crowded than your home beforehand.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because, I mean, that's quite common, but then you have to go forth.
[SPEAKER_00]: You still have to go forth.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that monk who's stuck in that familiar tradition of Buddhist monasticism needs to actually go forth from that.
[SPEAKER_00]: Needs to go forth, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Can he stop being a monk?
[SPEAKER_01]: But still, without... Yeah, without disrobing.
[SPEAKER_01]: Without disrobing.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, that's that's the thing, like... Can you still practice?
[SPEAKER_01]: Your practice should be defined by, like, as I said, it starts, of course, by sense restraint, virtue, learning the rules, but if you never upgrade it from that level, you are still defined by these random observances.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why, literally, virtue and my duty is the very first fetter that's sought upon abandons.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's exactly what it is.
[SPEAKER_01]: He leaves it without breaking it, but not holding it anymore, not holding it as an acquisition, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because you realize, ah, it's about the non-delight.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's about non-greed, non-aversion, non-delusion, that you get on account of sense restraint, if you made the right effort.
[SPEAKER_01]: So then, you can literally be a monk anywhere, in any circumstance.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because it's not about what you do.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not even, like, what you wear, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's just, like, an external statement for others.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's about what you're incapable of thinking.
[SPEAKER_01]: Why you're incapable of pursuing internally.
[SPEAKER_01]: Anything based on greed, aversion, delusion.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, non-delight brings dispassion.
[SPEAKER_01]: Change?
[SPEAKER_01]: Seeing the you-yourself in its core of your very being,
[SPEAKER_01]: are subject to change.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's enough to uproot your sense of ownership.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, in what you see, there is just what you see.
[SPEAKER_01]: In what you hear, there's just what you hear.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not like more, less, want, don't want.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, this is agreeable, this is disagreeable, this is comfortable, this is uncomfortable.
[SPEAKER_01]: None of it is besetting or overwhelming my mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: And it's... this is... your mind draws back from fame or reputation, really, from... Yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: ...disrepute.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, oh, those people, my family, might think that I'm this complete... Yeah, what other people will think about you.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: That will... that ceases to be your concern.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, he's been justly or unjustly criticized, doesn't matter.
[SPEAKER_01]: You will not lose perspective on it on account of that irrational fear of blame.
[SPEAKER_00]: Or, and the pressure to make sure that they have the right view of you.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, no, that's gone as well.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's rooted in your conceit.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if people... Again, you're trying to control that which is uncontrollable.
[SPEAKER_01]: Other people's opinions, literally.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, okay, many people can understand that.
[SPEAKER_01]: But one thing is to understand that on a rational level, and another thing is to let that rational level settle in, so you're emotionally unperturbed, in regard to blame and criticism.
[SPEAKER_01]: Even emotionally, it cannot be touched.
[SPEAKER_01]: Let alone mentally revolve around it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's why you will be unable to lose perspective.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if somebody criticizes you, you would be absolutely clear about where they're coming from, and you could see, actually, they have a point.
[SPEAKER_00]: I was completely wrong in that regard.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you wouldn't have a problem admitting it either.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because you're not irrationally defending your conceit, your gratuitous ownership.
[SPEAKER_01]: And equally, if you're criticizing, you realize that's absolutely ridiculous.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's even not true.
[SPEAKER_01]: Completely misses the point.
[SPEAKER_01]: But you wouldn't feel pressure to...
[SPEAKER_01]: I must correct and rectify the world and make sure that everybody knows the truth.
[SPEAKER_00]: Defend your honor.
[SPEAKER_00]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: Defend your honor.
[SPEAKER_01]: Defend your name.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, reputation, like, again, it's like sense-restraint.
[SPEAKER_01]: Initially, you want to practice sense-restraint, and you want to keep the vinaya rules, and you don't want to break that reputation.
[SPEAKER_01]: As in, you don't want to break the virtue.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if you never upgrade from that level, you're still remaining dependent on circumstances.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which means, if circumstances then criticize you, even if you haven't actually did anything to break your reputation, just somebody doesn't like you, or they disapprove of you in any other way, and then they just find things to blame you for, you'll be affected by it, because you stayed on that level where these things, where these things are subjected to that.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're depending on the circumstances not criticizing you, not blaming you.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, your your equanimity is based...
[SPEAKER_01]: Your equanimity is dependent on that.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's not equanimity.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's a very limited equanimity.
[SPEAKER_00]: Shaky ground, basically.
[SPEAKER_01]: Very shaky ground, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because, literally, so my my well-being depends on the opinion of others.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, I can't even...
[SPEAKER_01]: I don't have a say in how my own thoughts arise.
[SPEAKER_01]: I only have a say in whether I delight in them or not.
[SPEAKER_01]: And here I am, assuming I should have a say in how other people's thoughts arise and what they think of me.
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: All I can do is not delight in it, not try to reject it or resist it irrationally.
[SPEAKER_01]: Same what you do to yourself.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why that he knows it internally, he knows it externally.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's the same thing, same attitude in regard to both, or internally and externally.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, yeah, then you're kind of bulletproof for whatever happens externally.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, you basically left that shore where these things are happening.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're not there anymore.
[SPEAKER_01]: There's nothing for you.
[SPEAKER_01]: Nothing, nothing.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's impossible for anything to land on you.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because you're simply not there.
[SPEAKER_00]: You don't have to psychologize, or... No.
[SPEAKER_00]: ...the reasons that other people are saying these things to you.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, and that's another thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: You know, like when people sometimes say that, like, I don't know, somebody offends you, and you're really angry, and you can't... you still bear the grudge, and then you find out that that person was abused as a child, and now you're not angry with them.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, that's just psychologizing.
[SPEAKER_01]: You never uprooted the anger.
[SPEAKER_01]: You just basically updated the circumstances, and now this is acceptable for you to not be angry.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, you don't want to be angry in the first place, regardless of person who offended you, was sort of abused and went through lots of suffering or didn't.
[SPEAKER_01]: You don't want to be offended by full stop.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because offense is on you, it's not on what's being said.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if you need to justify the source of the offense as, ah, see, I forgive him because such and such, ah, you still blame what's being said for offense.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're not taking responsibility for it on the emotional level.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which means, sooner or later, that will have to change.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, sooner or later, you'll be back to suffer again on account of some other offense.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because what stops you to find out that, actually, no, they were not abused as a child, and they were not a victim.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then you can find out again, no, they really were.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then you can find out that they weren't.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you're fully thrown dependent on the worldly winds, praise, blame, fame, and you just, ah, left, right, trying to avoid one, failing to see that the other one will have to come because of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, seeing that the problem is not in the world, in the movements of the world,
[SPEAKER_01]: It's in your own delight, non-delight, resistance or craving against it.
[SPEAKER_01]: You stop doing that, it doesn't matter.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, you don't have to manage the world anymore.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's the true freedom.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, you're not burdened by action.
[SPEAKER_01]: The things you have to do, otherwise you'll drown in your own suffering.
[SPEAKER_00]: And, eh... the continuation of this Sutta, 7, in Gujarat 7, 49.
[SPEAKER_00]: This is perception number six.
[SPEAKER_00]: When a bhikkhu becomes accustomed to the perception of dukkha in anicca, an acute perception of fear or danger becomes settled in him towards indolence, laziness, slackness, heedlessness, lack of effort and unreflectiveness.
[SPEAKER_00]: Just as one would have fear towards one's executioner with a drawn-out sword.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, time is short, actually.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, so, yeah, anicca becomes established.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, because that's why, like, regardless of what you do, what you think, you remain subject to change, which means at any time it can occur in an unfavorable manner.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, once you recognize the weight of that, the gravity of that situation,
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, that's uncomfortable.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's the dukkha in that change.
[SPEAKER_01]: The inherent unpleasantness in that not being your own, not being in your own control, not having a say over your own life, fundamentally.
[SPEAKER_01]: It depends upon external random things, such as functioning organs, that you have no say in whatsoever.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you recognize that anicca correctly, you will be recognizing the discomfort of that situation.
[SPEAKER_01]: And the clearer it is, the more of the sense of urgency will develop.
[SPEAKER_01]: Even if I choose to ignore it, or rest, go to sleep, or whatever else, no, think about it, I remain subject to it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you can see...
[SPEAKER_01]: Which means, it's a dear... like, everything is at stake, at any given time.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you can see, you know, am I being lazy?
[SPEAKER_00]: Am I sitting back, relaxed, and enjoying things?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, that's the thing, and that's... you would also then understand what true laziness is.
[SPEAKER_01]: Sitting back and relaxing is not necessarily laziness.
[SPEAKER_01]: Mentally, as we discussed in that talk, delusion, delusion, that's what laziness is.
[SPEAKER_01]: Mentally giving in to oblivion, turning away, distracting yourself, ignoring.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can just spend the whole day laying on the bed, if you want.
[SPEAKER_01]: But not for a second, should you allow your mind to forget about the perilous situation that it's in.
[SPEAKER_01]: Undermined by change that's not in your control.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you'll be practicing contemplation and meditation, regardless of your body posture.
[SPEAKER_00]: But also, you can't entertain the idea that you've understood anicca, dukkha...
[SPEAKER_00]: Unless you're feeling that urgency.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, and there's no urgency.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: But that hasn't been the case.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, you're either in arahant, because there's no urgency, you're fully free, so there's nothing to burgeon about, or you don't even understand what anicca is.
[SPEAKER_00]: But it's a clear sign.
[SPEAKER_00]: There can be a clear red flag for you.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you practice anicca correctly, that discomfort of dukkha will be apparent.
[SPEAKER_01]: You cannot practice anicca and not feel the dukkha.
[SPEAKER_00]: But laziness can be a sign of that danger you're in, that you haven't understood.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: The fact that you can still turn and engage in laziness, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, that's what we said.
[SPEAKER_01]: Even, like,
[SPEAKER_01]: Satipaṭṭhāna, sakadāgāmī, anāgāmī, if you were to see them, he would be sort of trying to re-evoke the sense of urgency in them.
[SPEAKER_01]: He said, why?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, because there is still work to be done.
[SPEAKER_01]: And if he would see an arahant, he wouldn't try to invoke sense of urgency in him.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because there is nothing to be done anymore.
[SPEAKER_00]: So that's...
[SPEAKER_01]: Literally, to be done.
[SPEAKER_01]: Work to be done.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not like experiences that might happen to me if I'm lucky.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, literally, you and your effort is the sole determination.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you sustain the effort, and do it, and do it, and do it, the results will have to follow.
[SPEAKER_01]: If there are no results, it's either because you're not doing enough effort, or your effort is misplaced.
[SPEAKER_01]: As in, you're doing wrong things.
[SPEAKER_00]: Putting effort in wrong things.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're hoping things will just work out.
[SPEAKER_00]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: I'm just doing this randomly.
[SPEAKER_01]: But do you recognize what you're doing as a practice?
[SPEAKER_01]: It's work.
[SPEAKER_01]: Do you recognize that as pertaining to freedom from suffering, freedom from delight, inability to suffer amidst the worldly winds?
[SPEAKER_01]: Do you recognize that for fact?
[SPEAKER_01]: Do you see a relationship between the two?
[SPEAKER_01]: Or it's more like, yeah, yeah, my life's getting better, but I don't quite see the connection.
[SPEAKER_01]: I'm just doing this because, you know, it makes me feel good.
[SPEAKER_01]: Means you don't really know what the work is.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, how can you then do the work if you don't know what the actual work is?
[SPEAKER_01]: Hey, can you build me something?
[SPEAKER_01]: Build me a table.
[SPEAKER_01]: You don't have a clue how to build a table.
[SPEAKER_01]: How can you possibly build a table?
[SPEAKER_01]: First, you need to understand what the work of building a table is, to produce a table.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the work of non-delight.
[SPEAKER_01]: The work of penetrating through and understanding the nature of things.
[SPEAKER_01]: The work of knowing where the problem is.
[SPEAKER_01]: The problem is not in that somebody's in front of my door.
[SPEAKER_01]: The problem is that I can't help being affected by it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Either open the door, try to chase them, or open the door, let them in.
[SPEAKER_01]: Either way.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if you just think, oh, I must chase them.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you're making all this effort, sensory strain, sensory strain, completely wrong on a wrong basis.
[SPEAKER_01]: You don't understand where the problem is.
[SPEAKER_00]: But when you see that danger, you're surrounded by...
[SPEAKER_01]: It means you already did a fair amount of work.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because danger is not seen because the entire life, the entire existence is about, as I said, outrunning it and covering it up, keeping it at arm's length.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if you manage to see the danger, either circumstances force it upon you, but then, again, many people experience the danger and the peril and fear for their lives and so on, but they don't get wisdom on account of it, because the moment the circumstances change, they're back into their old ways.
[SPEAKER_01]: Some people, however, don't even need to experience the circumstances at all.
[SPEAKER_01]: All you need to do is recognize that they are subjected to all of this.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that, in itself, is all the danger you need.
[SPEAKER_00]: All the recognition.
[SPEAKER_01]: All the recognition you need, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because that recognition, as well, of being completely surrounded, or, you know, the executioner's sword is on your neck, you're tied up, at any point he's going to do it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: That could freak people, you know, that's... Yeah, well, they free them out because, again, they don't know what the problem is.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, you would think the problem is... you would think you can avoid the sword.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can't.
[SPEAKER_01]: He will cut your head off.
[SPEAKER_01]: But people don't realize that, so they still act out of this notion that they're in control of their life, so they just have to be extra careful and don't make a wrong move, so the executioner will cut their head off.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, it's not about making a wrong move.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why people quote that sutta to justify this ridiculous sensation watching practice of moving, moving, sitting.
[SPEAKER_01]: I must not let a second slip, because they'll chop my head off.
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: Your head's being chopped anyway.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the only thing you can really do that will make a difference there, it's not... not make a wrong move, because it makes no difference.
[SPEAKER_01]: He's there to cut your head off.
[SPEAKER_01]: He's basically abandoned that, which will be destroyed when he draws his sword.
[SPEAKER_00]: Right.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that can be next second, in ten years, doesn't matter.
[SPEAKER_01]: The sword is there.
[SPEAKER_01]: I see it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Do I still hold on to the body?
[SPEAKER_01]: Do I still hold on to my emotion?
[SPEAKER_01]: Am I still attached to my life?
[SPEAKER_01]: Am I still delighting?
[SPEAKER_01]: Abandon that before the sword comes.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not, okay, touching, touching, moving, moving, sitting, sitting, laying, laying, second, one, two, three, four.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're wasting your time.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's not the problem.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can't save this body from being chopped.
[SPEAKER_01]: By the executioner.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can abandon it before it's chopped.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you don't abandon it by focusing on it.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're abandoning it by removing the ownership that underlines it.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's underneath it.
[SPEAKER_00]: But you don't remove the executioner.
[SPEAKER_01]: You... it's inconceivable.
[SPEAKER_01]: So that whole, the famous sutra, you would be as careful, like, not to spill.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not to spill the water, because you'll cut the head off.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's a different story.
[SPEAKER_01]: But you would be as careful in the sense of, ah, I will not give in to delight, even to the point of spilling slightly towards it, because then I'm subjected to being killed.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not like I will freeze and spend the rest of my life in this catatonic stupor of meditation without making a slightest motion, because
[SPEAKER_01]: You have to recognize that that assassin, in that other certainty, who lives like your best friend, inside of you, that's you, basically.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's your own assassin, because you remain ignorant of death.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's inside.
[SPEAKER_01]: You cannot outrun that.
[SPEAKER_01]: You cannot escape that.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you can only escape in the sense of, ah, get rid of it or something.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you can only abandon that which he's about to assassinate.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you abandon it by seeing what's subjected to it.
[SPEAKER_01]: What is subjected to?
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, it's subjected to execution.
[SPEAKER_01]: This body is subject to the to the assassin.
[SPEAKER_01]: That is his goal.
[SPEAKER_01]: So I have a choice.
[SPEAKER_01]: Either ignore that and try to make the most of it, or abandon that which will be killed.
[SPEAKER_01]: Remove my ownership of it, through seeing the inherent danger and actually impossibility to own.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because if I'm true owner,
[SPEAKER_01]: If I'm truly in control of this life and this body, no assassin can come and kill me.
[SPEAKER_01]: But the fact that I am subject to death, means I'm subject to... my control is fundamentally subjected to non-control.
[SPEAKER_01]: So there's really no choice about it, in other words.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not like, oh yeah, but I don't mind the execution.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, you do.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because you value life.
[SPEAKER_01]: You value ownership.
[SPEAKER_01]: And this is completely opposite of that.
[SPEAKER_01]: To be taking away, ripping it away from you.
[SPEAKER_01]: So the only thing, the only reason you think you don't mind is because you're so intoxicated with your ownership, you don't even acknowledge the threat of a drawn sword.
[SPEAKER_00]: Ah, but no, he can't get me.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, get you.
[SPEAKER_01]: But then it's too late for you to do anything about it.
[SPEAKER_00]: But if you see the reason, you don't become afraid and...
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, you will probably be afraid initially, because you don't really know where the problem is, and what can I do, what can I not do.
[SPEAKER_01]: But the clearer you are about the practice, the less and less afraid you are, because you realize, well, this is inevitable.
[SPEAKER_01]: And also, it's not about me trying to control the uncontrollable, like body movement, never move, and only eat a little bit.
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's about not delighting when I delight.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, just remove delight, remove greed, aversion, distraction.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's it.
[SPEAKER_01]: You have closed the gates through which assassin and the executioner can come and kill you.
[SPEAKER_01]: And now, that's the true safety.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's the other sutra that...
[SPEAKER_01]: The monk was going around the forest saying, oh, this is so blissful, it's so blissful.
[SPEAKER_01]: And people thought, oh, he must be thinking about his previous former wives or whatever, because he's... so they're like, he's not happy with the monk's life.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then they called... they told the Buddha, they were to call him up.
[SPEAKER_01]: He says, what are you referring to when you say so blissful?
[SPEAKER_01]: Is it your previous lay life?
[SPEAKER_01]: He's like, what?
[SPEAKER_01]: No, no, no, no, no.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's the opposite.
[SPEAKER_01]: He said, when I was a layman, he was a prince, constantly in fear of his life, by his own family, by other kings, whatever, because he was next in line to the throne.
[SPEAKER_01]: So he never had a moment of peace.
[SPEAKER_01]: Wherever he was, he had to get guards with him.
[SPEAKER_01]: His palaces were guarded inside and outside.
[SPEAKER_01]: Constantly, he was constantly living in fear that he'll be killed.
[SPEAKER_01]: And he said, and now, after practice dhamma, and obviously fulfilled it, I'm living in this utter, complete,
[SPEAKER_01]: Wilderness of a jungle with tigers and elephants and, like, deadly things.
[SPEAKER_01]: My life is much more at risk now than it used to be.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yet, I feel complete ease and peace and not traces of fear.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that...
[SPEAKER_01]: So, when he remembers the previous life, he sees that disparity.
[SPEAKER_01]: How much worse off he was before.
[SPEAKER_01]: And it's just delightful for him to remember, like, how long he has come.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's the thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, with all the protection in the world, no.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because the reason for you being subjected to fear and danger is internally, because you delight in things that are subjected to fear and danger.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not because there is fear and danger.
[SPEAKER_00]: Right.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes, and no protection needed.
[SPEAKER_01]: No protection needed, because there's nothing to... That's what it's like.
[SPEAKER_01]: Whenever you... Like when we said in the previous recording, leading up to this,
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, you never, like, dare to leave the monastery or home, whichever way, because of the safety.
[SPEAKER_01]: Look, if there is a need for safety, it means you're protecting something.
[SPEAKER_01]: And if you're protecting something, it means you have taken up the ownership of that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which means there's dhamma missing there.
[SPEAKER_00]: And there's definitely pressure.
[SPEAKER_00]: There's pressure there.
[SPEAKER_00]: There's dukkha.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're subject to that.
[SPEAKER_00]: So then, the last perception.
[SPEAKER_00]: When a bhikkhu becomes accustomed to the perception of anatta, in what is dukkha,
[SPEAKER_00]: His mind is devoid of eye-making, mind-making and conceit regarding this conscious body and all external objects.
[SPEAKER_00]: It has overcome all measurements due to conceiving.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's exactly what I'm saying.
[SPEAKER_01]: Measurement due to conceiving is that.
[SPEAKER_01]: To the extent you conceived,
[SPEAKER_01]: To that measure, you are subject to losing, needing to protect it, safety, fear.
[SPEAKER_01]: To the extent you developed your ownership, to that extent you'll need to defend it.
[SPEAKER_01]: To that measure, you are subject to all the things that what you've appropriated is subjected to.
[SPEAKER_01]: Change, discomfort and so on.
[SPEAKER_01]: So you remove your conceivings, there's nothing you can be measured by.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's why seeing anicca correctly, subject to change, is experienced, felt unpleasantly, which is then lived as not mine, not myself, as an atta.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because the necessary basis for atta, for sense of ownership, and I am, I am the first, everything else is second for me,
[SPEAKER_01]: He's not seeing that that I am is subject to change, which is uncomfortable, which is not mine.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you are not yours, Putujana is not his, Arahant is not his.
[SPEAKER_01]: But Putujana thinks he is, while he's not his.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why Putujana is liable to suffering and everything else, because he lives the discrepancy of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Arahant doesn't think he is.
[SPEAKER_01]: He's not his.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's why you're able to free yourself from ownership.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because your ownership was just a misconception from the start.
[SPEAKER_01]: You never really owned things.
[SPEAKER_01]: Obviously, that is the start.
[SPEAKER_01]: As the Buddha said, ignorance is beginningless.
[SPEAKER_01]: There's no point where you made a mistake and became the owner.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, ownership is the beginningless.
[SPEAKER_01]: It shouldn't be there.
[SPEAKER_01]: You cannot own things, but not knowing that, that's how you own things.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that not-knowledge of ownership is beginningless.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's saṃsara, that's avijja.
[SPEAKER_01]: But that's why, once you understand that ownership is impossible, you cannot revert back to ownership.
[SPEAKER_01]: Nothing can happen that can revert you back from an arahant.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's irreversible because you're discerning what's there, basically, on account of which you used to mistake the ownership.
[SPEAKER_01]: So now the mistake is uprooted and you cannot possibly engage with it anymore.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can't knowingly, through wisdom, develop ignorance.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's mutually exclusive.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, developing that perception.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, developing the perception of another.
[SPEAKER_01]: And the Buddha said, not me, not mine, not I am.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's the contemplation that Sotāpanna should be cultivating, whatever he experiences.
[SPEAKER_01]: Present, past, future, feeling, perception, doesn't matter.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not me, not for me, not I am.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not mine, basically.
[SPEAKER_01]: Reminding himself of what he understood.
[SPEAKER_01]: Ah, not mine.
[SPEAKER_01]: Reminds me of the impossibility of that thing to be on in the first place.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, you're just keeping that position.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, contemplating anatta correctly, re-reveals anicca and dukkha.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, yeah, just...
[SPEAKER_01]: Contemplating anicca correctly, you will feel dukkha, you will experience anatta automatically, simultaneously.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, one, two, three.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can emphasize one, two, three, but the others are there with it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Anicca and dukkha and anatta.
[SPEAKER_00]: Those three things are recognized.
[SPEAKER_01]: The stronger that perception gets... Yeah, you're just basically fortifying those very things, the same things.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, that fortification of those perceptions is the work that needs to be done.
[SPEAKER_00]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: Just cleaning, cleaning, cleaning.
[SPEAKER_00]: Polishing.
[SPEAKER_01]: We use that similar in there.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Polishing and polishing and polishing and polishing and polishing.